A Finding Aid to the Jacques Lipchitz papers and Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1910-2001, bulk 1941-2001, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Jacques Lipchitz papers, circa 1910-1999; bulk 1941-1999; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973; Bassett, Bruce W.; 9.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-10, OV 11-12
  - Photographs, circa 1910s-1967; 1.10; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 8-10
    - Places, 1956-1964; 1.10.6; Archival Resource Key
      Some of the unidentified landscapes and views of buildings may be travel pictures. Photographs of the Lipchitz studio at Hastings-on-Hudson, NY show many finished pieces, maquettes, and works in progress. They also give a good sense of the space. The contact sheets include Lipchitz and his studio assistant in a few views. Also found are an undated photograph of Picasso's studio in Paris and one of "Atelier Halser."
      Additional photographs of places, including Lipchitz's studio at Pietrasanta, Italy, are found in the photograph album (Subseries 1.10.7), and may be enclosed with letters scattered throughout the correspondence (Subseries 1.1.2).
      Photographs, arranged by subject, are presented in rough chronological order within each folder. This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
      - "Atelier Halser" (Yves Hervochon, photographer), circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 51)
      - Building Exteriors and Interior, Unidentified, circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 52)
      - Landscapes, Unidentified, circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 53)
      - Lipchitz Studio, Archival Resource Key
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY, 1956-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 54)
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (Photographers: The New York Times, Sacha Parma, Whitestone Photo, and unidentified), circa 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 55)
          Oversized material housed in Box 10, F5
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (contact sheets; Gerald Hochman, photographer), circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 56)
      - Picasso Studio, Paris, circa 1930s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 57)
      - Oversized Photographs - Lipchitz Studio, Hastings-on-Hudson, NY, circa 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
        Oversized material scanned with Box 9, F55
    - Photograph Album, 1967; 1.10.7; Archival Resource Key
      All photographs were taken during the summer of 1967 in Pietrasanta, Italy. The first section contains both color and black and white prints; the second part is all black and white.
      Both sections were removed from the same 3-ring binder and retain their original collation. This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
      - "Jacques Lipchitz, Peace on Earth, Italy, Summer 1967" and "Jacques Lipchitz Studio Shots Summer 1967,", Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 58)
        Both sections were removed from the same 3-ring binder.
    - Negatives, Slides, and Color Transparencies, 1950s-1965; 1.10.8; Archival Resource Key
      Negatives, slides, and color transparencies are of artwork by Lipchitz. All artwork is unidentified except for a transparency of Sketch for Bull and Condor (watercolor and pencil on paper, created 1913). Two 35-mm color slides show Lipchitz judging a Yonkers Art Association exhibition in the 1950s.
      Additional negatives, slides, and color transparencies are among the catalogue raisonné records (Subseries 1.5). Arranged by record type, this subseries has not been scanned.
      - Negatives - Artwork by Lipchitz, circa 1961-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 59)
      - Slides (35-mm, color), circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 60)
        Artwork by Lipchitz
        Lipchitz Judging Yonkers Art Association Exhibition
      - Color Transparencies, circa 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 61)
        Lipchitz with Sculpture
- Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1961-2001; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 43.3 Linear feet Boxes 13-67, OV 68-69
  The Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz measure 43.3 linear feet and date from 1961 to 2001. The series consists mainly of materials related to Bassett's extensive audiovisual documentation projects concerning the life and art of the sculptor Jacques Lipchitz. Also found are paper records including letters, business records, printed materials, and paper production records related to the audiovisual projects. Other projects, unrelated to Lipchitz, include video and sound recordings related to Sidney Lifchez, IBM, Isamu Noguchi, the Storm King Sculpture Center, and Auguste Rodin.
  Original sound recordings and photographs from Deborah Stott's 200 hour oral history with Jacques Lipchitz are found, as well as detailed, typewritten summaries of its content. Documentation used in Bassett's film projects about Lipchitz include original film and sound recordings from Bassett's 40 hours of interviews with Lipchitz from 1971, and film documentation of the posthumous installations of Lipchitz's large-scale sculptures in Philadelphia, New York, and Israel in the late 1970s. In addition to the raw footage from these projects, which is incomplete, the collection contains workprint and final, edited works Bassett created in multiple versions and formats, and paper records documenting the film projects' creation, production, and later use.
  Among the papers related to the film projects are scripts, an index to original footage, programming notes, film lab records, exhibition materials, an extensive collection of questions about Lipchitz gathered from the public for the interactive project, and other production records. Other papers include letters from Lipchitz and his wife, business correspondence, financial records, contracts, project files, and printed materials.
  Records of other projects, unrelated to Jacques Lipchitz, are also found, including video and sound recordings from Bassett's projects about the designer Sidney Lifchez, IBM, the Storm King Sculpture Center, Isamu Nogichi, and Auguste Rodin. Other projects not created by Bassett but found among his papers include two news films related to John F. Kennedy during his presidency, a screenplay entitled The Man with Two Sides to His Head by Anthony Cave Brown, the film Man Is My Name, by Pierre Dominique Guisseau, and a portion of the film Dream on Monkey Mountain.
  - Jacques Lipchitz Letters, 1970; 2.1; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 13
    This series consists of letters written by Jacques Lipchitz, and one letter fragment written by Lipchitz's wife. One folder contains photocopies of eleven letters written by Jacques Lipchitz to unnamed correspondents between 1927 and 1931. Letters are in French and concern sculpture commissions and personal matters. Also found are two letters written by Lipchitz to Bruce Bassett about their work together and a fragment of a letter from Lipchitz's wife to Bassett.
    - Letters (1927 - 1931), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Location of originals is unknown
    - Letters to Bruce Bassett, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Business Records, 1968-2001; 2.2; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 13-14
    This series contains tax records, correspondence, invoices, contracts, releases, and project files concerning the work Bassett produced under the auspices of the Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation and Histor Systems, two organizations he founded. Both entities were concerned mainly with projects documenting the life and work of Jacques Lipchitz, and both contain materials related to the two main Lipchitz projects, namely the documentary and the interactive video installation. The Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation was dissolved in part because of the Lipchitz family's concerns that its existence would confuse and complicate transactions involving Lipchitz artworks after his death.
    The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
    2.2.1: Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation, 1968-1982
    2.2.2: Histor Systems, 1991-2001
    - Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation, 1968-1982; 2.2.1; Archival Resource Key
      The Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation was founded by Bruce Bassett in 1968. Projects carried out through the Foundation include the the audioguide created for the Brooks Memorial Art Gallery, the Deborah Stott Interviews (Subseries 2.4), Jacques Lipchitz Interactive Project (Subseries 2.5.2), Jacques Lipchitz Documentary (Subseries 2.5.3). The Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation dissolved around 1978, but Bassett carried on with his work related to Jacques Lipchitz under the auspices of Histor Systems (Subseries 2.2.2).
      Subseries includes financial records, organizational records, correspondence, contracts, and project files related to the major projects carried out through the Foundation. The Bylaws folder includes a list of the JLAF Board of Directors from 1971. Notable documents in Correspondence include a letter from Nelson Rockefeller to Lipchitz, and letters about the creation of a Jacques Lipchitz Sculpture Museum (which never came to pass). The Contracts and Releases folder includes the original media release signed by Jacques Lipchitz. The Brooks Memorial Art Gallery project files document the production of an audioguide in conjunction with a 1974 Jacques Lipchitz exhibition at Memphis, TN museum through correspondence, checklists, drafts of a script, and photographs. The documentary project files contain records of fundraising and distribution of the film, a list of music used, and correspondence describing changes to 1977 version of film. The interactive project files consist mainly of documents related to a demonstration of the interactive system in December, 1973.
      Additional documentation of the interactive project is found in series 2.2, Business Records, Histor Systems, and in series 5.2, Film Projects, Interactive Project. A long interview with Lipchitz and a large collection of photographs, both produced under the auspices of the Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation, are found in series 4, Interview with Jacques Lipchitz conducted by Deborah Stott.
      - Financial Records, 1968-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Bylaws, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Deborah Stott Letters, 1968-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Contracts and Releases, 1971-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Brooks memorial Art Gallery Project Files, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 8-13)
      - Documentary Project Files, 1974-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 14-17)
      - Interactive Project File, 1973-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Histor Systems, 1991-2001; 2.2.2; Archival Resource Key
      Bruce Bassett founded Histor Systems to continue his work on the Jacques Lipchitz interactive project, as well as some work connected to the Lipchitz Documentary, after the Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation was dissolved. Under this organization, Bassett also worked to promote the interactive system for use documenting other notable public figures, without success.
      This series primarily contains records relating to the presentation of the Lipchitz interactive project, which was usually presented under the title "Conversations with Lipchitz." There are also records relating to the Lipchitz documentary and its later releases with French and Spanish subtitles. Other records in the series include invoices mostly addressed to Hanno Mott, records relating to a demonstration of the interactive system in Israel, and an interactive project file that includes informative and promotional letters about Histor Systems, most notably addressed to Bill Gates and President Jimmy Carter (at the time, a prospective subject for an interactive project). The Interactive Project Files includes a list of Histor Systems directors in 1996.
      The last installation of the interactive system to be documented here was with the exhibition Lipchitz and the Avant-Garde: From Paris to New York, in 2001 at Krannert Art Museum, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. Krannert Art Museum records relate to the financial and logistical operation of the interactive system, as well as marketing and publicity for the exhibition.
      Subseries 2.5, Film projects related to Jacques Lipchitz, contains the actual audiovisual content of the interactive project and the Lipchitz documentary, as well as records related to their production.
      - Interactive Project File, 1991-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - Documentary Subtitle Records, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 20-21)
      - Financial Records, 1997-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 22-24)
      - Israel Demonstration Files, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 25)
      - Krannert Art Museum, Archival Resource Key
        - Staffing Invoices, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1)
        - Marketing, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 2-4)
        - Guest Log, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 5)
        - Visitor Response, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 6)
        - Staffing for Interactive Program, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 7)
        - Hanno Mott Correspondence, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 8)
        - Calendar, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 9)
        - Publicity, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 10)
        - Publicity Photographs, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 11)
          (Contains photographs of Bassett with Jacques Lipchitz)
        - Gertrude Stein Performance at Members' Reception, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Printed Materials, 1961-2001; 2.3; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 14, OV 68
    This subseries contains published material on Lipchitz collected by Bassett, as well as publicity for Bassett's Lipchitz documentary and interactive projects. A.M. Hammacher's book Lipchitz is inscribed by Jacques Lipchitz.
    - Articles about Lipchitz (Photocopies, 1942-1997), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
    - Internet Printouts about Lipchitz, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Book Research, circa 1968-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Lipcthiz Obituaries, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Jacques Lipchitz: Mother and Child, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Lipchitz by A.M. Hammacher, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - The Artist at Work: Jacques Lipchitz, Master Sculptor, Encyclopedia Brittanica Educational Corporation, 1968; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel (Item FC 317)
    - Corcoran Gallery of Art Exhibition Poster, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 21)
      Oversized item housed in OV 68
    - Publicity, Lipchitz Documentary, 1974-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Publicity, Lipchitz Interactive Project, 1972-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Oversized Exhibition Poster (Oversized material from Box 14, F21), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 68)
    - Oversized Publicity, Lipchitz Documentary (Oversized material from Box 14, F22), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 68)
  - Interview with Jacques Lipchitz conducted by Deborah Stott, 1968-1970; 2.4; Archival Resource Key; 8 Linear feet Boxes 14-22
    Deborah Stott, at the time a graduate student in Art History at Columbia University, recorded roughly 200 hours of conversation with the artist between 1968 and 1970 in Pietrasanta, Italy. The series contains a near-complete run of the sound recordings on 209 sound tape reels (1/4"), as well as detailed typewritten summaries of the subject content for each reel are available at the beginning of the series, and a 32 page transcript of the first reel. 183 of the reels are marked "first dub" and are presumably copies made from the original tape. 26 of the original sound reels are also found, for tape numbers 112-135 and 184-185, and are interfiled with their dubbed copies. Reels 137 and 165 are not extant, but typewritten summaries do exist for those reels. Also found are photographs that document Lipchitz's acquired collection of primitive and ancient art, which are often referred to by number in the interviews. Included are contact sheets, negatives, prints, and photocopies of prints.
    This interview was carried out under the auspices of the Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation and largely funded by a grant from the Ford Foundation.
    Some of the sound recordings have been digitized for research access.
    - Summaries and Transcript, 1968 July 31-1970 March 27; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 24-28)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 1-36, 1968 July 31-1968 September 27; Archival Resource Key; 36 Sound tape reels (Box 15, Item 1-36)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 37-72, 1968 Sept. 28-1968 Dec. 4; Archival Resource Key; 36 Sound tape reels (Box 16, Item 1-36)
    - Sound recordings, Reels 73-108, 1968 Dec. 4-1969 July 28; Archival Resource Key; 36 Sound tape reels (Box 17, Item 1-36)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 109-128, 1969 July 29-1969 Aug. 27; Archival Resource Key; 37 Sound tape reels (Box 18, Item 1-19)
      (includes original reels for #112-128)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 129-136, 138-158, 1969 Aug 28-1970 Jan. 13; Archival Resource Key; 36 Sound tape reels (Box 19, Item 1-29)
      (includes original reels for #129-135)
    - Sound Recordings, Reels 159-164, 166-185, 1970 Jan. 13-1970 Mar. 27; Archival Resource Key; 28 Sound tape reels (Box 20, Item 1-26)
      (includes original reels for #184-185)
    - Photographs of Jacques Lipchitz's Acquired Collection, Archival Resource Key
      - Contact Sheets and Negatives, #1-1540, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 27-29)
      - Contact Sheets and Negatives, #1-1540, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Contact Sheets and Negatives, #1541-2889, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 2-5)
      - Prints, #1-499 (Photocopies), circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 6-9)
      - Prints, #500-999 (Photocopies), circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 10-11)
      - Prints, #1000-1499, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 12-16)
    - Photographs of Jacques Lipchitz's Acquired Collection, Archival Resource Key
      - Prints, #1500-1999, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
      - Prints, #2500-2889, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 6-10)
  - Film Projects Regarding Jacques Lipchitz, 1971-2001; 2.5; Archival Resource Key; 28.2 Linear feet Boxes 22-46, 53-65, OV 69
    This subseries contains paper records, artifacts, motion picture film, video, and sound recordings created and used in the production of Bruce Bassett's film projects related to Jacques Lipchitz. Bassett originally shot over 40 hours of motion picture film with synchronized sound recordings in 1971. From this footage he developed the first incarnations of his two main projects: the Jacques Lipcthiz interactive project, also known as "Conversations with Jacques Lipchitz," and a documentary about Lipchitz. Both projects debuted to the public at the 1972 Jacques Lipcthiz retrospective exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City. After Lipchitz's death in 1974, Bassett shot additional footage documenting the casting of large-scale Lipchitz sculptures in Italy, and the installations of those sculptures in New York, Philadelphia, and Jerusalem, carried out by his widow, Yulla Lipchitz. This material was used in an updated version of the documentary, which was released around 1977. Subsequent releases occurred in the late 1980s and early 1990s. The interactive project was also exhibited in multiple versions, in a variety of formats as video and computer technology evolved, between 1973 and 2001. See the subseries descriptions below for more detail.
    The series is arranged as 3 subseries:
    2.5.1: Original Footage and Stock Footage, 1971-1981
    2.5.2: Jacques Lipchitz Interactive Project, 1972-2001
    2.5.3: Jacques Lipchitz Documentary, 1972-1994
    - Original Footage and Stock Footage, 1971-1981; 2.5.1; Archival Resource Key
      This subseries contains original footage shot by Bassett and his crew and used as the source material for his two film projects documenting Jacques Lipchitz. Bassett's initial filming took place in Italy in August and September of 1971, and later in Philadelphia, Miami, New York, and Jerusalem between 1976 And 1978. Footage from the shoot in Italy contains several long interviews with Lipchitz and footage shot in his Italian studio and foundry. All numbered camera and sound reels from the Italy filming are described in detail in the script book at the beginning of the series. Film and sound footage from the later shoots contain mainly documentation of the posthumous large-scale sculpture installations overseen by Lipchitz's widow, Yulla Lipchitz, as well as multiple interviews with her.
      120 of the 171 original sound reels from the Italy filming survive, but very little of the camera footage remains. In addition to original sound reels, a dubbed copy of all of the sound recorded in Italy is found on a smaller set of reels, so any missing original sound reels can be recovered from the dubbed copy. Four miscellaneous, sound-only reels of original sound recordings are also found. None of the original camera reels remain from the Italy shoot, but workprint copies of 20 of the 193 original camera and sound reels were made at a later stage in Bassett's work, possibly to edit new versions of his film projects. These workprints were named "archival prints" by Bassett and are the only remaining raw footage from the 1971 filming period in Italy. Some of them have splices, indicating portions were removed. Reels are listed by the new reel numbers assigned by Bassett when they were re-printed, but their original reel numbers, indexed and described in the script book at the beginning of the series, are also noted. Two unnumbered reels of original footage of Lipchitz working in his studio on the sculpture The Last Embrace are also found in this series.
      For later filming in the US and Jerusalem, original camera reels, some with sound on film, and separate original sound reels are found. There is no paper record of these shoots in the collection. Material is arranged by subject and date. Other raw footage found includes four camera reels of sculptures by Lipchitz from the Metropolitan Museum.
      Other source material in this series includes stock footage and stock soundtrack, produced by others but used in Bassett's Lipchitz projects, and a couple of short reels of sound effects and titles.
      Note that the workprint is silent 16 mm picture unless otherwise indicated, original sound reels are ¼" tape, and soundtrack is 16mm fullcoat magnetic stock. Some of the later foundry and installation footage was shot on reversal positive film with a magnetic stripe soundtrack, identified in the container listing as sound on film.
      - Italy Filming, Archival Resource Key
        - Script Book (Photocopies), circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 11-13)
        - Sound reels #1-14 and 25-49, 1971 August-September; Archival Resource Key; 38 Sound tape reels (Box 23, Item 1-38)
        - Sound reels #50-71, 73-81, 107, 123-128, 1971; Archival Resource Key; 38 Sound tape reels (Box 24, Item 1-38)
        - Sound Reels #129-166, 1971; Archival Resource Key; 38 Sound tape reels (Box 25, Item 1-38)